Inventory of the Colby E. "Babe" Slater Collection D-394
University of California, Davis General Library, Dept. of Special Collections
Colby E. "Babe" Slater Collection
1906-2014
1917-1957
University of California, Davis General Library, Dept. of Special Collections
Slater, Colby E.
D-394
11.9 linear feet
Colby E. "Babe" Slater (1896-1965) graduated from the University Farm School (now the University of California, Davis) in 1917. He served with the United States Army Medical Corps in France during the First World War. An outstanding athlete, Slater won Olympic gold medals for rugby in 1920 and 1924. Around 1927, he bought land in Clarksburg, California where he farmed for many years. Slater was active in organizations associated with athletics; agriculture; the University of California, Davis; and Yolo County, California. The Colby E. "Babe" Slater Collection (1906-2001, bulk 1917-1957) contains correspondence, diaries, publications, ephemera, photographic material, and realia. Most of the collection pertains to Slater and the United States Olympic Rugby Team winning gold medals at the Olympic Games in Antwerp, Belgium (1920) and Paris (1924). The collection also includes material related to the history of the University of California, Davis; the First World War; agriculture; and the history of Yolo County, California.
Access
Collection is open for research under regular Reading Room rules and copyright restrictions.
Acquisition Information
In December 2003, Marilyn Slater McCapes and Richard H. McCapes gave the Colby E. "Babe" Slater collection to Special Collections at the General Library of the University of California, Davis.
Biographical Narrative
Colby E. "Babe" Slater, was born on April 30, 1896 in Berkeley, California to Louise and John Slater. Babe, the youngest child, had two brothers and a sister. The Slaters lived in San Francisco before moving to Berkeley. The family's fortunes reversed when John Slater, a prosperous sea captain, died in 1908. Babe and his older brother Norman attended Berkeley High School, played on the school's athletic teams, and participated in sporting events on the University of California campus. In 1911 and 1912, Babe Slater led the Berkeley High School rugby team to county, regional, and state titles.
In 1914, Babe Slater left Berkeley High School to attend the University Farm School in Davis (now the University of California, Davis). The University Farm School, a branch of the University of California's College of Agriculture, offered a three-year course in the principles and practices of agriculture. While at the University Farm, Slater starred in rugby, football, basketball, and baseball. He served as Basketball Team Captain, Junior Class President, House Manager for the Calpha Fraternity, Thanksgiving Day Special Chairman, Picnic Day Parade Chairman, and Picnic Day General Chairman.
When Slater graduated from the University Farm School in May 1917, the First World War was underway. America declared war on Germany on April 6, 1917. Slater registered for the newly instated draft in June 1917, enlisted in the United States Army in September, and was promoted to Corporal in November. In the spring of 1918, he led a group of Yolo County "Liberty Boys" as they traveled by train from Woodland, California to Camp Lewis, American Lake, Washington, where they underwent intensive training for war. Slater's company arrived in Southampton, England on July 19, 1918 and then spent a few days at a rest camp in Cherbourg, France. Slater served with the Medical Corps, and he and his company were "on the move" from July to November in France and Belgium, tending to wounded soldiers, evacuating them from battlefields to hospitals, and setting up dressing stations. Often they came under fire from German aircraft and shelling since they had to work near the front lines. On November 11, 1918, an armistice was signed between the Allies and Germany, and the fighting stopped. Slater's company remained in France until April 1919, when they were able to sail back to America. From New York, Slater and other returning soldiers traveled by rail to California. On May 9, 1919, they received a heroes' welcome in San Francisco. Slater's military service ended May 23, 1919.
After Slater returned from the war, he raised sheep, hogs, and feed in Woodland, California, where he and his friend Robert (Bob) Lockhart managed a section of the Conaway Ranch. Still an outstanding athlete, Slater played and coached for the Woodland, Yolo Post No. 77, American Legion's football and basketball teams. Slater led Woodland's American Legion football team to the Northern California Championship in 1927.
Due to the soaring popularity of American football, rugby had virtually disappeared from the United States except in California. In 1920 when the Olympic Games Committee allowed the formation of a United States Olympic Rugby Team, it was no surprise that every team member was a Californian. Slater was one of the first players chosen for the team. The 1920 Olympic Games were held in Antwerp, Belgium. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team was the only team that dared to challenge the powerful French team, and the French eventually condescended to play the inexperienced Americans. On September 5, 1920, the Americans won gold medals by unexpectedly beating the French, 8-0.
In 1924, the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team was again made up of Californians. Babe Slater was chosen as team captain. His brother Norman was also on the team. At the 1924 Paris Olympic Games, only three teams entered the rugby competition: France, Romania, and the United States. Although the Americans had been well received in London, where they had played three exhibition games against English rugby teams, the French public was hostile toward the U.S. team. The French rugby team, regarded as the most skilled in the world, easily beat the Romanians, 61-3 on May 4, 1924. On May 11th, the United States defeated Romania 37-0. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team was mainly made up of basketball and American football players who did not have much experience playing rugby, yet their size, fitness, and athletic ability made them formidable opponents. On May 18, 1924, the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team won gold medals by defeating France 17-3 at Colombes Stadium. Angry French fans rioted in the stands, assaulted American supporters, and jeered the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team during the medal ceremony. After the American victory, the French government apologized for the behavior of the French fans. Due in part to the fans' violence, rugby was not included in future Olympic games.
Circa 1927, Babe Slater moved from Woodland to Clarksburg, California and bought rich farming land located in the Holland Land Company subdivision. Slater farmed there for close to thirty years raising crops including: alfalfa, asparagus, barley, beet and carrot seeds, dry beans, peas, safflower, sugar beets, tomatoes, and wheat. Norman Slater left his job as a mechanic for Associated Oil Company in San Francisco and moved his family to Clarksburg so that he could farm with his brother. Babe Slater married Virginia Cave (1909-1991) in 1932, and they had one daughter, Marilyn. In 1955, Marilyn graduated from the University of California, Davis. She married Richard McCapes in August 1955. Soon after his daughter married, Slater retired from farming.
Slater was active in many University of California, Davis organizations including the Cal Aggie Alumni Association, Friends of the Davis Campus, the UC Davis Alumni Agricultural Advisory Committee, the UC Davis Alumni Scholarship Foundation, and the secret society Sword and Sandals. He and Mrs. Slater were often honored guests for Picnic Day at UC Davis. Slater was a Picnic Day parade judge in 1956. In 1956 and 1957, he arranged for reunions of the classes of 1916 and 1917 to be held on the UC Davis campus during Picnic Day.
Also active in the local community, Slater was a member of the Woodland, Yolo Post No. 77, American Legion and the Woodland Elks Lodge, No. 1299. He was elected president of the Yolo County Farm Bureau in 1951 and 1952, and, over the years, he and Mrs. Slater went on many Farm Bureau trips including travel to Australia, Belgium, Canada, Germany, Japan, and Mexico.
Colby E. Babe Slater died on January 30, 1965. Later that year, the Calpha agricultural fraternity established the Colby E. "Babe" Slater Memorial Athletic Award at the University of California, Davis. This annual award and the "Babe" Slater Perpetual Athletic Trophy went each spring to the Davis student selected as Athlete of the Year. In addition, Slater was posthumously inducted into the Woodland Athletic Hall of Fame (1973) and the Cal Aggies Athletic Hall of Fame (1980) at the University of California, Davis.
A list of sources consulted and a detailed chronology follow this biography.
Sources:
Blum, John M., William S. McFeely, Edmund S. Morgan, Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr., Kenneth M. Stampp, and C. Vann Woodward. The National Experience: A History of the United States. San Diego, Calif.: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1985.
Collegiate Underdogs Claim Gold Medal. Accessed on-line on March 23, 2004 at http://www.rugbyallamericans.org/history.html
Coppo, Richard. "The History of Rugby in the Olympic Games." Rugby Magazine, Feb.-March 2004. Accessed on-line on March 17, 2004 at http://rugbymag.com/archive/2004/march/march.htm
Hickey, Dan, comp. In the Beginning. Accessed on-line on March 17, 2004 at http://www.pacificcoastrugby.com/template.php?sid=10#top
Jenkins, Mark. "An American Victory in Paris." >Historical Rugby Articles. Accessed on-line on March 19, 2004 at http://wesclark.com/rrr/history.html
Larkey, Joann Leach. Cooperating Farmers: A 75-Year History of the Yolo County Farm Bureau. [Woodland, Calif.]: Yolo County Farm Bureau, 1989.
Memorial Book, Department of Animal Science, University of California, Davis. Entry for Robert R. Lockhart (1893-1963). Accessed on-line on Feb. 4, 2004 at http://animalscience.ucdavis.edu/memorial/lockhart.htm
"Rugby at the 1924 Olympics." Historical Rugby Articles. Accessed on-line on March 17, 2004 at http://wesclark.com/rrr/history.html
Scheuring, Ann F. Abundant Harvest: The History of the University of California, Davis. [Davis, Calif.]: UC Davis History Project, 2001.
Walters, Shipley. Clarksburg: Delta Community. Woodland, Calif.: Yolo County Historical Society, 1988.
Chronology
1873-1882 University of California students at Berkeley played informal disorganized "football" games against each other and local high school teams.
1882 Rugby enthusiasts from the San Francisco Bay Area converted the University of California to the game of rugby.
1883-1885 The University of California continued to play Bay Area rugby clubs, improved greatly, and was soon defeating most teams.
1886 The University of California's first head football coach, O. S. Howard, brought the game of American gridiron football from the East Coast to the Berkeley campus. American football immediately became popular in California.
1889 July 9. Brother, J. Herbert Slater was born to Louise and John Slater.
1891 Feb. 7. Sister, Marguerite Slater was born to Louise and John Slater.
1894 Jan. 23. Brother, Norman B. Slater was born in San Francisco to Louise and John Slater.
1896 April 30. Colby E. "Babe" Slater was born in Berkeley to Louise and John Slater. The first modern Olympic Games were held in Athens, Greece.
1900 Rugby was on the program for the second Olympic Games in Paris. Great Britain, France, and Germany sent rugby teams. The French won the gold medal.
1906 The University Farm, a branch of the University of California's College of Agriculture, was established in Davis, California. Due to the brutal nature of American football, its burgeoning professionalism, and fighting between University of California and Stanford University fans, as well as President Theodore Roosevelt's censure of the game, high schools, colleges, and universities in California dropped American football in favor of rugby.
Circa 1906-1914 Bay Area fans became more and more interested in rugby. As many as 26,000 flocked to big games between the University of California and Stanford University.
1908 Jan. 8. Father, John Slater died.
1909 January. Formal instruction began at the University Farm School in Davis. The University Farm offered a three-year course in the principles and practices of agriculture. Virginia Cave (later Mrs. Colby E. "Babe" Slater) was born in Clarksburg, California.
1910-1914 The earliest University Farm School teams played rugby but called it football.
1911, 1912 Babe Slater led the Berkeley High School rugby team to Bay County League championships, the Northern California title, and the State title. Brother, Norman B. Slater played half back on the team.
1914 January. Three female students (the first at the University Farm School) arrived from Berkeley to spend a few months on the Farm. One of them was Babe Slater's sister, Marguerite Slater. June 28. Sarajevo. In an act that led to the First World War, Gavrilo Princip assassinated Archduke Franz Ferdinand, heir to the throne of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. July-August. Austria-Hungary declared war on Serbia, Russia, and Belgium. Germany declared war on Russia, and after Germany demanded from Belgium free passage for German troops, Germany declared war on France. Great Britain declared war on Germany after Germany invaded neutral Belgium. August-September. British forces crossed to France in an attempt to halt the German advance. French and British troops pushed the Germans back at the first battle of the Marne. Then the French marched north to beat the Germans in a race to control vital ports in the British Channel. The enemies established stable battle positions, creating the "Western Front," a solid line of opposing trenches that stretched from the Channel to near Nancy, France.
1914-1917 Babe Slater left Berkeley High School to attend the University Farm School at Davis. He starred in rugby, football, basketball, and baseball. He served as Basketball Team Captain, Junior Class President, House Manager for the Calpha Fraternity, Thanksgiving Day Special Chairman, Picnic Day Parade Chairman, and Picnic Day General Chairman.
1915 February. Germany proclaimed a war zone around the British Isles. May 7. Lusitania, a British luxury passenger liner traveling from the United States was sunk off the coast of Ireland by a German submarine. Almost 1,200 civilians were killed, including 128 Americans. Autumn. California's high schools, colleges, and universities started playing American football again. Rugby's popularity began to die out in America. Autumn. The University Farm School stopped playing rugby in favor of American football. Slater was one of only eighteen men from a student body of 296 who reported for the University Farm's first American football team.
1916 February-December. The Germans launched an offensive against the French at Verdun. Losses on both sides were heavy--about a million men. No strategic advantages were gained by either side. April. The United States threatened to sever diplomatic ties unless Germany changed its method of submarine warfare. July-November. The British conducted an offensive along the Somme River at the Western Front, but suffered their heaviest losses without making substantial gains.
1917 January. Germany announced that their submarines would sink all ships belligerent or neutral. The United States broke off relations with Germany. March 18. German submarines sank three American ships. April 6. The United States declared war on Germany. May. The United States House and Senate passed a selective service bill in order to recruit a large army and spread the obligation to serve among all qualified men age twenty-one to thirty. May 18. After completing a prescribed three-year course in agriculture, Slater graduated from the University Farm School. Early June. Over nine million American men including Slater registered for the draft. July-November. Enduring extremely rainy and muddy conditions, British forces conducted an offensive against German lines near Ypres, Belgium. There were heavy casualties. Finally, Canadian troops captured the village of Passchendaele. Sept. 23. Slater joined the United States Army. He served with the Medical Corps in France during the First World War. October-November. The Eastern Front had collapsed along with the Russian Army. After the October Revolution, the Bolsheviks took power in Russia and began to negotiate with Germany for peace. This allowed Germany to concentrate on the Western Front. Nov. 1. Slater was promoted to Corporal.
1918 Spring. German forces launched a major offensive on the Western Front. Allied lines manned by war-weary French and British troops crumbled. Circa May. A crowd assembled in Woodland, California at the Southern Pacific depot to see off the Yolo County "Liberty Boys." Slater led the group of forty-two boys, who entrained for Camp Lewis, American Lake, Washington to begin intensive training for war. May-June. Germans pushed the French back to the Marne River, close to Paris. American troops stopped the Germans at Chateau Thierry. June 27. American soldiers, including Slater, left Camp Lewis by train. Along the route to New York, townspeople cheered the troops and gave them candy and cigarettes. July 3-11. Slater was based at a camp in New York, and he visited New York City before being sent to war. July 12. Slater's company sailed from New York on the S.S. Olympic. The enlisted men endured poor conditions aboard the ship. July 19-20. Slater's company arrived at Southampton, England. July 21-25. Slater's company was at a rest camp in Cherbourg, France. July-August. Germans struck at a sector of the Marne between Rheims and Soissons. Americans helped to turn the attack and participated in the French counteroffensive that cleared out the sector. July 26-Aug. 24. Slater's company was based at St. Nazaire, France. General Pershing inspected the camp. Aug. 28-Sept. 6. Slater's company was based at Nogent, France. September-October. Meuse-Argonne offensive. The Allies pushed through German lines. Costly, but crucial American victories near St. Mihiel, Verdun, and Sedan as well as French and British successes routed the Germans and all but defeated their army. The Germans were driven out of France, and the Allies advanced into Belgium. Sept. 26-Oct. 4. Slater's company moved through Avocourt, Very, and Epionville, evacuating wounded soldiers to hospitals. They spent six terrible days under heavy shellfire and attack from enemy airplanes before they could leave Epionville. Oct. 13-17. Slater's company was at Revigny, France. Oct. 19-25. Slater's company was at Boesinghe and Ypres, Belgium. Slater noted that Ypres was "shot up pretty badly." Oct. 25. Slater's company spent the day hiking from Ypres to Roulers. Slater noted that they passed by, "nothing but devastated country--worse than the imagination could ever stretch it--for miles and miles all that could be seen was torn-up ground that resembled a choppy sea with great tanglements of barbed wire and railroad tracks." Oct. 25-30. Slater's company was at Roulers, Belgium. Oct. 30-Nov. 5. Slater's company hiked from Roulers to the Waregem area and to the front lines. They tended to the wounded and set up dressing stations. The Germans were shelling and bombing Belgium from the air. Nov. 3. Slater and Jim Gregory volunteered to go to Oudenaarde to find out the status of the dressing station, which was in the City Hall. The Germans were shelling, and their airplanes were firing on troops. The bridge across the Schelde River to the German line was only about 300 yards from the City Hall. Nov. 5-9. Slater's company was at Roosebeke, Belgium. Nov. 9. The Kaiser abdicated. Nov. 11. In the Forest of Compiegne, an armistice between the Allied forces and Germany was signed and fighting stopped. Nov. 10-26. Slater's company was in Oudenaarde, where they put up a dressing station, but no patients came because hostilities had ceased. There was considerable celebration in the city over the declaration of an armistice. Nov. 26-Dec. 7. Slater's company was at Izegem, Belgium. December. Slater's company was based at Proven, Belgium. They took day trips around the country and often were the first to pass through devastated areas. When a group of them went to no-man's-land to gather wood, they saw: bodies of men and horses, trenches, graves, barbed wire, shells, machinery, downed airplanes, and churned up ground. They took souvenirs off of a German airplane. Dec. 19. Slater received a Christmas box. Dec. 24-25. Slater and other soldiers took the early train to Brussels. They got a room, had a good meal, and celebrated Christmas. Crowds cheered the Americans.
1919 Jan. 4-March 23. Slater's company was based at Ceton, France. When they left, the whole population of Ceton came to see them off. Jan. 27. General Pershing reviewed American troops including Slater's company at Belleme, France. March 24-April 7. Slater's company was near St. Nazaire at Camp Guthrie, an embarkation camp. The men underwent physical exams before sailing for America. April 8-20. American soldiers including Slater were at sea on the U.S.S. Virginian. The immaculate ship was newly refitted to transport troops. April 20-May 2. American soldiers including Slater returned to the United States. They docked at New York, got off a ferry at Long Island Terminal, and boarded trains for Camp Upton. Crowds cheered them wherever they went. April 22-23. Slater was on leave in New York City. May 2-9. Slater and other soldiers departed Camp Upton by train. After crossing the United States, they arrived in Oakland, California early in the morning, took a boat to San Francisco, were in a parade down Market Street to City Hall, and then took streetcars to the Presidio. May 23. Slater's military service ended. June 28. The Allied Powers and Germany signed the Treaty of Versailles and officially ended the "war to end all wars." Returning veterans organized Yolo Post No. 77, American Legion, in Woodland, California.
Circa 1919-1926 Slater settled in Woodland. Slater and Robert (Bob) Lockhart managed a 9,000 acre section of the Conaway Ranch, where they raised sheep, hogs, and feed.
1920s Slater played and coached for the football and basketball teams of the Woodland, Yolo Post No. 77, American Legion.